<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sincere preacher prouing that in whom is adulation, auarice, or ambition, he cannot be sincere. Deliuered in three sermons in Dartmouth in Deuon, vpon I. Thes. 2. 5.6. By Walter Wylshman, Mr. of Art, and minister of the Word there.</title>
            <author>Wylshman, Walter, 1571 or 2-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114199</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849427</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849427</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15797)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1504:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sincere preacher prouing that in whom is adulation, auarice, or ambition, he cannot be sincere. Deliuered in three sermons in Dartmouth in Deuon, vpon I. Thes. 2. 5.6. By Walter Wylshman, Mr. of Art, and minister of the Word there.</title>
                  <author>Wylshman, Walter, 1571 or 2-1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 89, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Ionas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14574:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14574:1"/>
            <p>THE SINCERE PREACHER: PROVING THAT IN whom is Adulation, Auarice, or Ambition, he cannot be ſincere.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN THREE Sermons in <hi>Dartmouth</hi> in <hi>Deuon,</hi> vpon 1. THES. 2. 5. 6.</p>
            <p>By WALTER WYLSHMAN, Mr. of Art, and Miniſter of the Word there.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>If yee know theſe things, bleſſed are yee if yee doe them.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decoration or printer's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Ionas Man.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14574:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14574:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND right graue and vertuous Matrone, <hi>and my beſt approued good Patroneſſe</hi> at greateſt neede; Miſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s MARY COT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON, wiſe to the right Reuerend Father in God, WILLIAM the Lord Biſhop of the Dioceſſe of <hi>Exon;</hi> the glorious comforts of grace here, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe of immortalitie and eternitie in glorie hereafter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of the ſons of men (Right Worſhipfull Patroneſſe) that all riuers goe into the <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. 7</note> Sea. Some think they doe it to doe their homage,
<pb facs="tcp:14574:3"/> and pay tribute to that place, from whence they receiued their beginning. So hath it been my long nine yeeres longing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, euer ſince I haue had a doore opened (by your friendly meanes) to enioy and imploy my poore Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall talent, in teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my grateful remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of your vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, though by me of you then deſired fauours in thoſe daies of my trials (al which trials the trier of hearts knowes came not on me for any ſingularity,
<pb facs="tcp:14574:3"/> but of meere ſimplicitie and ſinceritie of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) that there might paſſe backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to you ſome ſmall ſlender drops of thoſe fuller ſtreames of your then more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie beneuolence and beneficence, &amp; euer ſince moſt gratious cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance towards me. So that I may ſay to you as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> did to a friend of his, <hi>tibi quod poſſum debeo &amp; quod non poſſum.</hi> I am indebted to you in the higheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of my abilitie, and in a higher ſtraine then I am
<pb facs="tcp:14574:4"/> able to reach vnto. In ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement whereof (ſeeing other hoped-for meanes faile me) I be ſeech you to accept of theſe three Sermous, treating of the properties of a ſincere Preacher, being the firſt diuulged fruits of mine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue twenty yeeres labors in the Ministerie. Which I preſent not vnto you with the beſt thought of requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of your fauours, but as a bill of mine hand what I owe, and how deeply I am ingaged. All which if vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peruſall you finde (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede
<pb facs="tcp:14574:4"/> they are) but rude and rough hewed, yet I hope the worth of their ſubiect (compared with the rockineſſe and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſoile and ſeate where they were bred) will winne ſome fauour from your friendly &amp; fauour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able aſpect. Howſoeuer it be, this wil breed me ſome contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that by theſe I haue indeuoured what in me lieth, to make knowne mine vnfayned ſenſible thankfulnes, for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue and vnrequitable kindneſſes. And whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:14574:5"/> is wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting in me, I pray the God of all fulneſſe to fulfill in you, making you the plant of his owne right hand, being planted in the houſe of the Lord to <note place="margin">Pſal. 92. 14.</note> bring forth more fruite in your age, and to be fat and floriſhing. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death ſhall approch to ſhut vp the full period of your age-worne daies, for your fauours ſhewed to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, well may you bee able then to conſolate your decaied ſpirits, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with good <hi>Nehemiah: Remember me O my God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:14574:5"/> this: and wipe not out the kindneſſe that I haue ſhewed to the houſe of God, and on the officer thereof.</hi> I humblie take my leaue, <hi>Dartmouth</hi> in <hi>Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiere</hi> this October 14. 1614.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deuoted in al humble dutie, Walter Wylſhman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:14574:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14574:6"/>
            <head>THE SINCERE PREACHER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. THES. 2. 5, 6.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neither did we euer vſe flattering words, as yee know; nor coloured co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, God is record.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neither ſought we praiſe of men, neither of you, nor of others.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He whole ſcope and bent of this our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, in the former part of this Chapter, is, to perſwode the Theſſalonians to perſeuere in the conſtant profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that doctrine, which hee, and his fellow teachers had taught them, &amp; they had heard of them. And to this end he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14574:7"/> diuers reaſons: As firſt, that <note place="margin">V. 1.</note> their entrance was not in vaine, but with ſuch ſound doctrine ſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated with ſincere liuing, as that they dared to appeale to their knowledge and conſcience for the truth thereof. 2. That it was ſuch <note place="margin">V. 2.</note> doctrine, as that they reſuſed not to ſuffer at <hi>Philippi,</hi> many reprochfull diſgracements, wrongs and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for the confirmation thereof. 3. All which notwithſtanding, they <note place="margin">V. 3.</note> were bold to preach the ſame after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vnto them of Theſſaloni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ca. 4. That this was done without all <note place="margin">V. 4.</note> manner of in-ſinceritie in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in affection, or in the manner of doing: in doctri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne without er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, in affection without vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in the manner of doing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out guile. 5. On the contrary, it <note place="margin">V. 5.</note> was done in all manner of ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: For as wee were allowed of God (ſaith hee) that the Goſpell ſhould bee committed vnto vs; ſo wee ſpeake not as they that pleaſe men, but God.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14574:7"/>
            <p>Now in this text hee proceedeth to proue his fourth reaſon, that there was none inſincerity in their doctrine at all, by remouing ſuch faults as vſually make doctrines vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound or inſincere, and the faults which he laboureth to remoue, are three capitall faults in my text, which are as noyſome to ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in doctrine and religion, as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, famine, and ſword, are to ſoundneſſe in a Common-wealth. The firſt of theſe is Adulation; the ſecond Auarice; the third Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Adulation; <hi>for we vſed no flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering words as you know:</hi> Auarice, <hi>nor coloured couetouſneſſe God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord:</hi> Ambition, <hi>Neither ſought we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V. 6.</note> 
               <hi>praiſe of men, neither of you, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> For the remouing of the firſt, becauſe it is more palpable, hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales to their owne knowledge. For the ſecond, which is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he appeales to Gods record. And for the third of Ambition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for praiſe, or promotion, hee cleares it in the ſequels by his owne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14574:8"/> practice, and thinkes if he free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of theſe three, that he ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently confirme his aſſertion of their ſincereneſſe, not onely in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, but alſo in the manner ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: taxing by the way the falſe teachers with theſe vices, of flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, couetouſneſſe, and ambition in their doctrines; which in whom ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they are, they proue the very corrupters of their miniſtery, and the very cut-throates of the whole Church. I will therefore briefly ſpeake of each of theſe in order, ſo far as they ſhall belong to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe: And firſt of flatterie; wherein I will obſerue theſe foure circumſtances: Firſt, what Adulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is. 2. How manifold it is. 3. How dangerous it is. 4. That the Miniſter that is a flatterer is not ſincere. For the firſt; what it is, the Grecians deriue this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to flatter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifieth meat, becauſe (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>they that are ſuch ſerue not the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus Christ, but their owne bellies,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14574:8"/> 
               <hi>and with faire ſpeeches and flattering deceiue the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with which is the Latine word <hi>Adulari,</hi> deriued by the Grammarians from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth ſeruile or baſe; for ſo are all flatterers, becomming mercenarie <note place="margin">Iude, ver. 16.</note> ſlaues, hauing mens perſons in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration becauſe of aduantage. So that flatterie is, when any one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth or extolleth others for ſuch things, as they are not to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or extolled for; and that to this end, that he may obtaine ſome ſuch thing, as he leaudly and vnlawfully deſireth to get at their hands. In which kinde of dealing there lie lurking two horrible vices: the one, that hee doth falſly and fainedly, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praiſe, or thinke, or doe ſuch things as he thinketh will bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to others, ſo that therein hee is a diſſembler and ſlauiſh. The other vice is, that he doth not this, either for the glory of God, or the good of the partie praiſed; but to currie fauour to himſelfe, and to ſeeke his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14574:9"/> owne aduantage, and this is ſeruile alſo: and for this cauſe flatterers are compared to dogs, which fawne to be fed, as may bee ſeene in <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> the falſe fawning Orator, who to wrong innocent <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpared not <note place="margin">Act. 24. 2.</note> to extoll vniuſt <hi>Felix.</hi> And in the men of Tire, who to purchaſe their owne peace, forbare not, againſt God and conſcience, to aduance godleſſe <hi>Herod,</hi> to bee as God, which their doubling and daubing how it diſcouered them to bee baſe and ſeruile, all men may iudge.</p>
            <p>The parts of this falſe flatterie are two; <hi>aut exim loquendo diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur aut tacendo,</hi> by ſpeaking, or by concealing it is diſcerned. By ſpeaking, as when they ſo ſeeke to pleaſe them that they hope to bee graced by, as that they ſpeake any thing that will humour them; as the 400. falſe prophets that were fat fed at <hi>Iezabels</hi> table, when they perceiued that <hi>Ahab</hi> their King was diſpoſed to make warre againſt <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> they framing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14574:9"/> to feed his fancie, faid, Goe vp, for the Lord ſhall deliuer it into the hands of the King: Like as the flatterers of <hi>Herod</hi> did, before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, who perceiuing the pride of <hi>Herod,</hi> a man that deſired ſo much to bee great, that hee ſhewed himſelfe to be an angelicall diuell: they ſpake to him like the diuell to <hi>Heuah, Ye ſhall be as Gods: Vox dei non hominis,</hi> the voice of God and not of man. As the Pope's ſhaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings now call their horrid Father, <hi>Papa noſter deus,</hi> the Pope our God. Whereas had they any grace, they would ſay in effect, as faithfull <hi>Michaiah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ahab, If thou goe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. King. 22. 17.</note> 
               <hi>vp, thou ſhalt not proſper, bitt all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſhall be as ſheepe without a ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, &amp;c.</hi> And as <hi>Phoſion</hi> a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, notably anſwered his King <hi>Antipater,</hi> who reqniring of him a thing vnreaſonable, I would (Sir) do for your ſeruice all that is reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable (ſaid he) but you cannot haue me both a friend and a flatterer. And as <hi>Agamemnon</hi> ſaid in like caſe to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14574:10"/> 
               <hi>Menelaus,</hi> being requeſted to ioyne with him in a thing vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; <hi>My wits I would enioy with thee, but mad with thee I would not be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other part of flattering is by concealing, when as a man remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the Heathens Maxime, <hi>Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium amicos veritas odium parit:</hi> that is, Flatterie gets friends, and plaine dealing fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, is afraid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue ſuch faults, as by his place he is bound to doe, but either by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſoweth pillowes vnder great mens arme-holes, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">Ezec. 13. 18.</note> or by his daubing healeth their hurts with ſweete words, ſaying, <hi>Peace, peace, when there is no peace,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iere. 6 14</note> as <hi>Ieremy</hi> reproueth: theſe like Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan beguile with vnfaithfulnes, and like <hi>Iudas</hi> deſire to pleaſe with kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling kiſſes: whereas had they any faith, charitie, or conſcience, they would with bold <hi>Paul</hi> tell reproue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> that he is to be blamed, and with diſcreet <hi>Nathan,</hi> diſcouer <note place="margin">Sam. 12 7.</note> to recouerable <hi>Dauid</hi> that hee had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14574:10"/> ſinned, and with vndaunted <hi>Elias</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uow that, to taunting King <hi>Ahabs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. King. 18 18.</note> face, that by him and his baſe <hi>Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim,</hi> all Iſrael was troubled. And theſe are the kinds of flatterie. Now followeth the third part of my diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and that is how dangerous flatterie is.</p>
            <p>It is ſo dangerous as that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſthenes</hi> ſaid fitly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. i. It is farre better to fall into the hands of Rauens, then of flatterers: for Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens deuour but the bodies of dead men, and theſe many times euill men: for it is oftentimes a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God to be denied buriall, as was ſeene in <hi>Iehoiakim,</hi> that was <note place="margin">Ier. 22. 19.</note> buried as an Aſſe is buried, that is, was drawen and caſt without the gates of Ieruſalem: but flatterers oftentimes corrupt and defile the mindes of liuing and good men, as may bee ſeene in <hi>Caius Caligula,</hi> who was for a certaine time a good Prince, but the flatterers which hee had about him, by their immeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14574:11"/> praiſes, made him become (as ſaith <hi>Suetonius)</hi> a monſter of men, aſſuming on him not only the name of great <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and of the great God himſelfe; for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf ſo much adored of theſe ſycophants, he fell perſwaded that no man durſt euer enterpriſe any thing againſt him, and ſo commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hee a thouſand cruelties, and ſtrange and horrible wickedneſſes, ſpending his time and power in all exceſſe, wantonneſſe, and riotouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; wherein hee neuer ceaſed to wallow and tumble himſelfe, till he was ſuddenly maſſacred and ſlaine: The like you haue heard of the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers of <hi>Abab</hi> and of <hi>Herod,</hi> who <note place="margin">1. King. 12 Acts 12.</note> brought them to their fearefull ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines and deſtructions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one ſaith of flatterers about great men, that they are worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dogs about <hi>Lazarus;</hi> for theſe dogs licked <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſores for his good, but flatterers licke the ſores of great ones for their hurt: for if they perceiue any vices in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14574:11"/> which are their ſoule-ſores, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they extoll theſe vices with the names of vertues, neere in alliance with theſe vices: as their crueltie, they call magnanimitie; their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digalitie, liberalitie; their luxurie, humanitie; their couetouſnes, good husbandry; their pride, cleanlineſſe; reuenge, manlineſſe; and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, kindneſſe and ſuch like. So that well doth the Philoſopher co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare a flatterer, for his imitating, to an Ape that will doe any thing; for his counterſeiting, to a falſe iemme or pretious ſtone that ſeems and is not; for his deceiuing, to a ſhadow that appeares and is not; for his biting, to a viper that woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth deadly; for his killing, vnto poyſon that deſtroyeth ſpeedily: All which dangers of flatterers well perceiued <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> who aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from a low eſtate to bee Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Rome, and feeling himſelfe not able to endure thoſe Syren ſongs of flatterers, willingly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke all his imperiall dignities to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14574:12"/> liue againe in a priuate life; which he did for aboue tenne yeeres ſpace, and neuer repented him whileſt he was a priuate man, that he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyled himſelfe of the Empire: for as <hi>Flauius Vopiſcus</hi> reporteth of him in the life of <hi>Aurelian,</hi> hee would often confeſſe, that nothing was harder then to know how to rule well; for foure or fiue (ſaith he) will aſſemble and make a plot toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deceiue the Emperour, after they will ſay all with one voyce what they will haue him doe: The Emperour, who is incloſed in his houſe, cannot know the truth of things as they paſſe, but by neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is conſtrained to vnderſtand no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what pleaſeth them to tel him, and make him vnderſtand; ſo doe they cauſe him to giue offices to men by themſelues in poſt, which merit them not at all, and make him caſt out ſuch as beſt deſerue them for the good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. What ſhould be ſaid more? to make ſhort (ſaith <hi>Diocleſian)</hi> a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14574:12"/> good wife and a vertuous Prince is bought and ſold by ſuch people. Behold the words of <hi>Vopiſcus,</hi> who euidently ſheweth that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> was diſcontented to be Emperour, becauſe he was gouerned, mauger his beard (as they ſay) by flattering Courtiers, which cauſed him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe his eſtate. And therefore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily delt <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the tyrant with <hi>Damocles</hi> his flatterer, for his faire words full of perill, cauſing a table to bee ſpread before him with all kinde of dainties and delicates, and withall enioyning him to ſit at this table, bid him often to eate of theſe delicates, who hauing a ſharp ſword hanging ouer his head by a ſmall haire with the point downwards, durſt not taſte any of them for the feare of the preſent danger; ſo ſaid <hi>Dionyſius</hi> are thy faire flatteries, howſoeuer in ſhew very glorious, yet I durſt not taſte of any of them, becauſe of the dangers that lay hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in them. Thus you ſee the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of flatterers, they are the canker
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14574:13"/> and very bane of Church &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Now I deſcend to the fourth part of my diuiſion, to wit, that the Miniſter that vſeth it is not ſincere.</p>
            <p>My reaſons are theſe: Firſt, it is <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 2.</note> required of the diſpoſers of Gods ſecrets, that they ſhould bee found faithfull: where faithfulneſſe is, there is ſincereneſſe; but there is no faithfulneſſe at all in them, that for fauour or feare, ſinne on the right hand or on the leſt: on the right hand by flattering indulgence, as counting great ſinnes of great men ſmall ſinnes, and ſmall ſinnes no ſinnes, or common ſinnes as ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; or at leaſt preach mercy where is no repentance; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are like thoſe that the Prophet ſpeaketh of, <note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 28. 21. Ezech. 13. 18. Ezech. 22. 28. Icr. 6. 14.</note> that will tranſgreſſe for a morſell of bread: theſe are they that ſow pillowes vnder mens elbowes, and heale the breaches of the people with ſweete words. Wherein they deale like gloſing Chirurgions, that meeting with a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14574:13"/> feſtred ſore, or with proud fleſh, in ſtead of lancing &amp; corroſiuing, vſe gentle ſtrokings and incarnatiues; and ſo the one makes the ſore ten times worſe, and the other the ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh very much greater; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as ſuch patients in the ende curſe ſuch daubers; ſo God and man wil at laſt curſe ſuch flatterers. For ſo ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Woe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 20.</note> 
               <hi>bee to them that ſpeake good of euill, and euill of good, which put darknes for light, and light for darkneſſe, that put bitter for ſweete, and ſweete for ſower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon why the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is not ſincere, is, becauſe that whereas hee being a Miniſter and meſſenger of God, ſhould ſpeake as God ſpeaketh; hee changeth his courſe, and ſpeaketh as man fanſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. God ſpeaketh deepely, and to the heart, hee lanceth the ſpirit, and woundeth the inward parts: So ſhould the Miniſter ſpeake. He bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſhew the people their <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 1.</note> tranſgreſſions, and the houſe of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14574:14"/> their ſinnes. He muſt ſhew forth the mercy of God, and not hide his iudgements. He hath the Lords bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe in hand, and therefore muſt be couragious. But a flatterer aimes at mens fauours, and feares their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures. When he ſeeth a theefe, he runneth with him, and is partaker <note place="margin">Pſalm. 50. 18.</note> with the adulterers. Hee chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with the times, and will not ſtriue againſt the ſtreames. But what do they? They denie God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray his truth, and deceiue his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Of ſuch the ſpirit ſpeaketh, <hi>a Wo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>vnto them that haue a double heart, and to the wicked lips.</hi> And, <hi>a double</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 1. 18 Luk. 2. 23.</note> 
               <hi>minded man is vnconſtant in all his waies:</hi> and, <hi>he that is not with mee is againſt me:</hi> and, <hi>hee that gathereth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 8. 21.</note> 
               <hi>not with mee, ſcattereth:</hi> and, <hi>how long halt yee betweene two opinions? If the Lord be God, follow him; but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 6. 4. 15.</note> 
               <hi>if Baal be he, then goe after him.</hi> And againe, <hi>what communion hath light with darkneſſe, and what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? Curſed is hee that flattereth the people, and is</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14574:14"/> 
               <hi>vnfaithfull in the Lords worke.</hi> Thus you haue heard what flatterie is, and the kindes and parts of it, and the danger thereof, and that there is no ſincereneſſe in the Miniſter that vſeth it. Whence we may ſee the force of our Apoſtles aſſertion, <hi>Receiue our doctrines for wee are no flatterers.</hi> Obſerue the vſes.</p>
            <p>The firſt vſe is, It teacheth euery Miniſter to take heed of flattery, let them vſe gentleneſſe, but not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; fairneſſe, but not fainedneſſe: let them endeauour to pleaſe the people, but no further then God may bee pleaſed alſo. It is reported, that <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great had two friends that he much eſteemed; the one for faireneſſe of condition, and the other for his faithfulneſſe in counſell: his pleaſant friend was <hi>Hephaeſtion,</hi> but his faithfull friend was <hi>Craterus. Hephaeſtion</hi> his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant friend would diſpleaſe him in nothing; but <hi>Craterus</hi> his faithfull friend would not pleaſe him but in iuſt and good things: whereupon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14574:15"/> 
               <hi>Craterus</hi> was called the friend of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King, but <hi>Hephaestion</hi> the friend of <hi>Alexander:</hi> ſo that by how much <hi>Alexander</hi> the King, was greater then <hi>Alexanders</hi> perſon; by ſo much a faithfull friend is better then a pleaſant friend. And thus muſt euery good Miniſter be in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, hee muſt bee an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſtion,</hi> pleaſe him in euery thing; but in reſpect of man, hee muſt bee <hi>Craterus,</hi> pleaſe him but in good things; as our Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 2</note> 
               <hi>man pleaſe his neighbor in that which is good to edification:</hi> but if men will not be pleaſed in this, but looke to bee pleaſed in their ſinnes, then it is better to pleaſe God then men; for as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 10.</note> 
               <hi>If I ſhould ſo pleaſe men, I were not the ſeruant of Christ.</hi> And to this end, becauſe men wil not common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be pleaſed with that which God is pleaſed with; therfore God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth <hi>Ieremie</hi> his Prophet, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <note place="margin">Ier. 1. 7. 8. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt goe to all that I ſend thee, &amp; whatſoeuer I command thee</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14574:15"/> 
               <hi>ſhalt thou ſpeake:</hi> he ſaith further; <hi>feare not their faces, lest I destroy thee before them; for behold, I haue made thee this day a defenced city, and an iron pillar, &amp; walles of braſſe againſt the whole land.</hi> And againe he ſaith, <hi>Let them returue vnto thee, but returne not vnto them; thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15. 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſhalt bee a conſuming fire, and they ſhall bee ſtubble before thee.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> ſought to refuſe the meſſage and thought himſelfe ouer ſimple to goe vnto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> God anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>certainly I will bee with thee:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 12. Exod. 7. 1. 2. Mat, 10. 27. 28.</note> and after he ſaith, <hi>I haue made thee Pharaohs God, and thou ſhalt ſpeake all that I command thee.</hi> So Chriſt ſaith, <hi>What I tell you in darkneſſe, that ſpeake you in the light, &amp; what ye heare in the eare, that ſpeake ye on the houſes; and feare yee not them that kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule; but rather feare him that is able to destroy both body and ſoule in hell.</hi> The conſideration hereof euer moued the Prophets and Apoſtles to warrant their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14574:16"/> with authority from God, and to ſet apart all feare when they ſpeake in his name. When <hi>Ahab</hi> reproued <hi>Elias, Art not thou he that troubleth Iſrael?</hi> hee anſwered, <hi>I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. King. 18. 18.</note> 
               <hi>haue not troubled Iſrael, but thou and thy fathers houſe, in that ye haue for ſaken the commandements of the Lord, and thou hast followed Baalim.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is bold with the Princes of Iuda and Ieruſalem, &amp; ſaith, <hi>Heare the word of the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ye Princes of Sodome, hearken vnto the law of our God, O people of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah. Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> is nothing <note place="margin">Mat. 14. 4.</note> afraid to tell <hi>Herod,</hi> a mighty Prince, <hi>It is not lawfull for thee to haue her to wife. If Balake would</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Numb. 24. 13.</note> 
               <hi>giue mee his houſe fall of ſiluer and gold</hi> (ſaith <hi>Balaam) I cannot paſſe the commandement of the Lord, to doe good or bad of mine owne mind, what the Lord ſhall command, that ſame will I ſpeake.</hi> So that theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that for fauour or feare flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the people, are worſe then <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> that was but a wizard. And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14574:16"/> thus you heare what is the Miniſters dutie, namely, to deale ſincerely, and not to flatter for any reſpect.</p>
            <p>The ſecond dutie is for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that if the Miniſter ought to ſpeake ſincerely without flatterie, then the people ought to haue ſound eares and hearts, to heare without pride; for where pride is in the heart of the hearer, hee will not ſuffer wholſome doctrine with <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 3.</note> his eare, but hauing his eares it ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after his owne praiſe, he will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the luſts of his proud heart, get him an heape of teachers, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh; for ſelfe-loue ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing blinded his iudgement, hee thinkes he muſt walke on without all controlement: whereupon <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith truly; <hi>Seeſt thou a man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 26. 12.</note> 
               <hi>wiſe in his own conceit, there is more hope of a foole then of him:</hi> therefore his counſel is, <hi>ſpeake not in the eares of a foole, for he will deſpiſe the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 9.</note> 
               <hi>of thy words.</hi> And hereof come theſe ſlanders againſt them that ſpeake with moſt ſincereneſſe, of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14574:17"/> deſcribing of men, and of pointing at men in the publike, and ſuch like; For as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>A wiſe man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 4. 16.</note> 
               <hi>feareth and departeth from euill, but a foole rageth and is careleſſe.</hi> And, <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 12.</note> 
               <hi>a ſcorner loueth not him that rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him, neither will he goe into the way of the wiſe:</hi> whereas poore ſoules did they know who ſpeaketh in the Miniſter, <hi>viz.</hi> God, and what hee ſpeaketh, <hi>viz.</hi> his word; and to what end he ſpeaketh, <hi>viz.</hi> for their good, they would feare the author, and loue the meanes, and imbrace the end, and finding the ſecrets of their hearts to bee made manifeſt, they would fall downe on their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and worſhip God, &amp; ſay plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 25.</note> that God is in the Miniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as the Apoſtle ſaith. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath no purpoſe to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, therefore he hath no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to bee reproued. And heere hence is it, that when <hi>Ieroboam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. King. 12. 31.</note> gaue himſelfe ouer to commit wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe with greedineſſe, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that hee might follow his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14574:17"/> without all kinde of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, the holy Ghoſt noteth, that he ſet vp to bee prieſts of the loweſt and baſeſt of the people; ſuch as had neither will nor wit, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor conſcience, nor courage to reproue him; and by this meanes he made al Iſrael to ſinne with him. A policy that the diuell hath long practiſed, as the moſt ſtrong ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemme ſtill to vphold his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkeneſſe and ignorance by. Here hence came in our impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations of the Eccleſiaſticall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, of the moſt populous and the moſt freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted places (if you marke it) in this land, that priuate men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing away theſe Church-liuings, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitants might either content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with a Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> lack-lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as <hi>Micha</hi> did with a running Leuite for ten ſhekles of ſiluer by <note place="margin">Iudg. 17. 10.</note> the yeere, and ſo be without all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: or elſe if they hire a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher by a voluntary contribution, their paying might bee as a meanes of his pleaſing them, by flattering
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14574:18"/> and ſoothing them in their ſinnes. For as <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Syrake</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 29. 26.</note> ſaith, <hi>where a man is a ſtranger or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friended, he dares not open his mouth.</hi> And here hence is it, that in many of theſe populous and vntaught places; ſinne doth not onely crawle in corners, but euen ſtandeth vp and walketh and ietteth in the ſtreets with a whoriſh forehead that will <note place="margin">Ier. 3. 3.</note> not bee aſhamed, as <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith, and he yeelds a reaſon of it, cap. 23. 14. <hi>For the prophets ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, that none can returne from their wickednes.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you my brethren all preſent, I beſeech you, I ſay, to heare the word of God with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and conſcience, and pray for mee that I may deliuer it with ſuch ſoundneſſe and ſincereneſſe, that Chriſt our Soueraigne may keepe regiment in our hearts by the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his word, that Satan the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit being caſt out, hee may no more returne amongſt vs. You know what Chriſt telleth his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14574:18"/> Matth. 5. 13. <hi>Ye are the ſale of the earth:</hi> and, <hi>ye are the light of the world.</hi> Now all know that ſalt muſt needs be ſharpe to a rotten or greene wound; and light muſt needs be painfull to a feeble or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eye: yet euen as the patient will willingly vndergoe the diſpleaſure of the cure, rather then hee will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe the pleaſantneſſe of the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; ſo muſt we doe to bee freed of our ſoules maladies and miſeries. A good Phyſition muſt needs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet his ſicke patient befor hee can heale his diſeaſe: and a good Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion muſt lance and rip vp fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred wounds, before he can apply helpfull and healing incarnatiues. We are ſpirituall Phyſitians and Chirurgions, the word of God the ſoules potion, and the wine &amp; oyle of the ſoules ſores is committed to vs, that by vs it might be applied to ſeaſon, ſupple, and ſalue all mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. If it ſeeme vnpleaſing, yet it is moſt profitable, therefore endure it; which that you may doe with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14574:19"/> and cheerfulneſſe, I will ſhut vp this point with that worthy ſaying of a faithfull Orator of <note place="margin">Titus Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius, lib. 3.</note> Rome, called <hi>Quintius Capitolinus,</hi> who on a time making an Oration to the Romans, after hee had liuely ſhewed them their faults, in that they ceaſed not to diſobey their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, whereby ſome great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and confuſion might fall to the Common-wealth, addeth in the end, theſe words: Maſters, I know well that a man may vtter more pleaſant talke, and tel you of things more plauſible; but as for me, my nature is not to flatter, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſity cauſeth that I loue ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to tell you true things then pleaſant. I haue a good mind to pleaſe and content you, but I loue much better to preſerue and guard you from falling into deſtruction, how little thanke ſoeuer I haue of you. Theſe remonſtrances and words of this good man were of ſuch efficacie, ſaith <hi>Titus Liuius,</hi> by the pure and natiue truth which he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14574:19"/> ſhewed vnto the people, without flattery, that hee appeaſed the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and diſcontentments of the City. So I doubt not (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) but that ſeeing I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale (with our Apoſtle) to your knowledge, and conſciences, that my carriage in ſpeaking vnto you, hath been without flattery, in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere plainneſſe; but that in the end I ſhall attaine to <hi>Salomons</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, namely, <hi>he that reproueth a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28. 23.</note> 
               <hi>man, ſhall find more fauour at the length, then hee that flattereth with his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14574:20"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. THESS. 2. 5.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Nor coloured couetouſneſſe, God is record.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue heard (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in our beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Ieſus Chriſt) that the Apoſtles be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was, to perſwade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians to perſeuere in that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which hee and his fellowes had taught them. And to this end he produced diuers reaſons, the laſt and not the leaſt whereof was, that they had taught them in all ſound ſincereneſſe; and to this end he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth in this verſe and the next to remoue ſuch capitall faults, as might taxe them of inſincereneſſe, and theſe are three in number; to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14574:20"/> wit, Adulation, Auarice, and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition: which three are as noiſome to ſincereneſſe in religion and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as peſtilence, ſword, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine are to ſoundneſſe in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Of the firſt (of Adula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) I haue ſpoken alreadie: now followeth the ſecond (of Auarice) in theſe words: <hi>Neither vſed wee co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured couetouſneſſe, God is record.</hi> Wherein as in the former of Adula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it was more groſſe and palpable, hee appealed to their knowledge; ſo here in this ſinne of couetouſnes, becauſe it is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; ſecret, he appeales to Gods record, ſaying, <hi>Neither vſed wee coloured couetouſneſſe, God is record.</hi> And as for the third, of Ambition, either for praiſe or profit, he cleeres it in the ſequels by their owne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and thinkes that if he free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of theſe three, hee ſhall ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently confirme his aſſertion of their ſincereneſſe not only in doctrine, but alſo in the manner thereof. Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the way the falſe teachers
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14574:21"/> with theſe three, which in whom ſoeuer they are found, they prooue the corrupters of their Miniſterie, and the ruinaters of the Church. Now in following of this ſtreame of couetouſneſſe, I will obſerue the ſame order, that I did in the former of flatterie, for I will handle theſe foure circumſtances: firſt I wil ſhew what couetouſneſſe is. Secondly, how manifold it is, and what are the parts thereof. Thirdly, how foule and monſtrous a ſin it is. And fourthly, that the Miniſter that is carried away with it, cannot be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. Finally, theſe heads being handled, I will draw foorth ſome vſes, and the remedies that wee are to make of it. For the firſt what it is, the Latines deriue this word A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice from <hi>Aueo &amp; ab auro vel are,</hi> ſo that they make couetouſnes to bee an immoderate deſire of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or gold. The Greekes call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth an immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate deſire to haue more; ſo that how much ſoeuer the couetous man
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14574:21"/> hath, yet not therewith contented he ſtill deſireth more. In like ſenſe the Hebrewes call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is an ouer earneſt deſire of gaine, which is neuer without oppreſſion and wrong. Hence then I may thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Couetouſneſſe is a baſe affection of the minde, ariſing from miſtruſtfulneſſe of God in his prouidence, whereby one doth ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderatly deſire earthly riches, as that neuer contented with that which he hath, he ſtill deſireth more then he hath, reſpecting neither right nor wrong done to others, to the intent that hee may attaine his deſire for himſelfe: all which being obtained, he ſtill wanteth as well that hee hath as that hee hath not: for that which he hath he dareth not enioy for feare of neceſſitie, and hee ſtill vexeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the want of that hee hath not, becauſe he would abound: ſo that ſtill wanting the vſe of that hee hath, and the poſſeſſion of that he hath not, he is euer vexed with woful perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> Which definition conſidered
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14574:22"/> with his cauſes, will appeare to bee the more abſolute. The efficient cauſe whereof is infidelitie, euen a miſtruſting of God in his alſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent prouidence, and a truſting in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine riches. And therefore our Apoſtle termes couetouſneſſe ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, becauſe the couetous man at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes that to riches, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to God, <hi>viz.</hi> truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The matter of his deſire is worldly gaine, which (like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world) is mutable and fading. The formall cauſe is his immoderate deſire of riches, which cannot bee ſatisfied. The finall cauſe is <hi>Philautia,</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſet himſelfe alone aloft, and this monſter, like a <hi>Cerberus,</hi> hath three heads, <hi>viz.</hi> feare of pouertie, loue of pleaſure, and loue of glorie. Whereupon Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> rightly compares Auarice to a ſtrumpet in a Ladies habit, ſitting on a chariot ſupported with foure wheeles, <hi>viz. Faint courage, Inhumane cariage, Contempt of God,</hi> and <hi>Forgetfulneſſe of death.</hi> This chariot he makes to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14574:22"/> be drawne with two blacke horſes, the one he nameth <hi>Rauine,</hi> and the other <hi>Nigardſhip.</hi> To theſe both there is but one carter, and he is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Deſire to haue.</hi> This carter driueth with a whip hauing two cords, the one named <hi>Appetite to get,</hi> and the other, <hi>Dread to forgoe.</hi> Thus you ſee what couetouſneſſe is, and how ſhe is mounted. Now if yee expect, that I ſhould ſet open and anatomiſe vnto you al the parts and members of this huge monſter Couetouſneſſe, I confeſſe that it ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth my reach: for as it is ſeated in the ſoule, which is a ſpirit, ſo it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from the affection or deſire, which is infinite, and therefore it being in nature infinit, her parts are alſo infinite, they cannot bee num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. Therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of this monſter Couetouſneſſe, which is but one, ſaith, that it is the roote <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 10.</note> of all euill, which is innumerable. So that if it be the roote of all euill, then it is the roote of idolatrie, the roote of impietie, the roote of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14574:23"/> the roote of blaſphemie, the roote of ſimonie, the roote of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the roote of briberie, the roote of parricide, the root of homicide, the roote of theft, the root of lying, of extortion, of oppreſſion, of all falſe dealing, of lying, the roote of contentions in the Church, the root of brabling and brawling in the Common-wealth. And as it is by nature ſpirituall, ſo it prieth into euery corner, and pierceth into eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie heart; it annoyeth our Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, it infecteth our Diuines, it choketh our Lawyers, it woundeth our farmers, it baneth our Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, it murthereth our tradeſmen, it bewitcheth our Merchants, it ſtingeth our Merchants, it ſtingeth our mariners, oh curſed co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe! it is the poyſon of all things, the wound of Chriſtianitie, and the bane of all godlineſſe: for couetouſneſſe marreth all, it marres all euery where, in all places, in all degrees, amongſt all perſons. It marreth mariages; for it coupleth old dotterds with young giglots;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14574:23"/> it marres hoſpitalitie, for it ſhuts the doores againſt the poore; it marres almeſdeeds, for it cloſeth the hand and heart againſt the needie; it marres religion, for it makes a ſhew of godlineſſe without the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer thereof; it marres profeſſors, for it barres their practiſe; it marres the Miniſterie, for it choketh zeale; it marres the Magiſtrates, for it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth iuſtice; it marres all things, for it is a very plague. By all which you may geſſe of the vniuerſalitie of the parts of couetouſneſſe. If you will haue her parts more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious and more compriſed, I will gather my ſelfe within the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Philoſophie, which makes the parts of Auarice to bee theſe three, according to the three chiefe kindes of her actions: the firſt is to get greedily: the ſecond is to keepe needily: and the third is to ſpend ſparingly and miſarly. More briefly, her parts are <hi>Capacitas, repacitas, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacitas:</hi> that is againe, her greedie getting, her needie keeping, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14574:24"/> her miſerable ſparing.</p>
            <p>For the firſt part Capacitie, which is an immoderate and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt holding of that which he hath, whereby he makes more reckoning of his riches and worldly mucke, then of his neighbours neceſſity and miſerie: ſuch was the holdfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Diues</hi> in the Goſpell, that <note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> not once moued with poore <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his miſerie, would not giue one crumme to eaſe his hunger; and his reaſon was (as it ſeemes) his loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to depart from any thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wedded to his wedge, and his diſpaire, as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Quod ſi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hor. Sat. Lib. 1. ſat. 1.</note> 
               <hi>diminues, vilem redigetur ad aſſem:</hi> if he ſhould once leſſen his mine, he doubted it would come to a mite: ſo that in his wee may ſee an heart ſet vpon riches, and riches vpon an heart; heapes of wealth like the hils that Wants caſt vp, <hi>Cumuli tumuli,</hi> euery hill is a graue, and euery heap a tombe to burie himſelfe in.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Rapacity, that is, that greedy deſire of gaine, which makes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14574:24"/> them that are infected therewith, not to reckon of the liues of the owners thereof, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith. <note place="margin">Pro. 1. 19.</note> Nay they are ſo greedily ſet vpon gaine, as that they care not for their owne liues neither, as may be ſeene in that golden-humored <hi>Midas,</hi> who obtaining his requeſt, that all that he touched ſhould be turned into gold, wrought his owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhment, for gold could not feede him; and therfore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>they that will be rich,</hi> that is (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 9.</note> greedily deſire it) <hi>fall into the ſnares of the diuell.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt</hi> ſaith, that couetouſneſſe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies infinite and vnſatiable, which is not leſſened, either with plenty, or want.</p>
            <p>The third part of couetouſneſſe is Tenacity, which is a baſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerly hoording vp of wealth with a miſtruſtfull wretchedneſſe, lothing to affoord himſelfe any comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſe of al his great ſtore and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of his riches: but as <hi>Salomon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5. 16.</note> ſaith, <hi>hee eateth his bread in the</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14574:25"/> 
               <hi>darkneſſe with much griefe, and in his ſorrow and anger.</hi> And as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>riſeth early, and goeth late to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 127. 2. <hi>Hor. Sat. Lib. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>bed, and eateth the bread of careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Such an one was <hi>Vuidius,</hi> that <hi>Horace</hi> ſpeaketh of, that aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in wealth, would not afford himſelfe clothes, but went in a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talized coate; for which miſerlines his ſeruants ſlue him, ſaith the Poet. And ſuch an one was the churle in the Goſpell (as it ſeemes) for vntill he had more corne then his barnes could hold, hee neuer ſaid to his ſoule, Take thine eaſe, eate, &amp; drink, and take thy paſtime: but when he thought hee had meate enough, God would not leaue him time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but told him, that in that inſtant night his ſoule ſhould bee taken from him. Thus you ſee co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe diſplayed with her parts. Now it is eaſie to ſee how fowle and monſtrous a ſinne it is.</p>
            <p>Couetouſneſſe is ſo vgly and monſtrous a ſin (as you haue heard) that it is the mother-ſinne, and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14574:25"/> of all other ſinnes, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinnes are but as it were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and factors to this ſinne, and ſerue but for porters, to fetch and bring in her liuing. For ſhe makes Symonie her drudge, Bribery her drudge, Vſurie her drudge, Deceit her drudge, Swearing her drudge, Lying her drudge, &amp;c. Oh what a diuell incarnate is this, that ſetteth ſo many vices aworke, and hath ſo many retainers and vnderlings to ſerue her turne! No maruell then if couetouſneſſe bee compared to the vnmercifull graue, to vnſatiable death, to all-deuouring hell, which can neuer be ſatisfied. <hi>Burſa auari, os diaboli</hi> (ſaith one), the purſe of a couetous man is the mouth of the diuell, which is alwaies open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, but ſhut to giue: like <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemus</hi> in <hi>Antro,</hi> who had <hi>omnia ſe aduorſum ſpectantia nulla retror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum:</hi> all towards him, but none from him: ſee his picture in <hi>Alc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon,</hi> who being willed by <hi>Croeſus</hi> to goe into his treſure-houſe, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14574:26"/> take as much gold as he could car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie away with him, prouided for that buſineſſe a long hanging gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment downe to his ankles, &amp; great bootes, and filled them both; nay, he ſtuffed his mouth, and tied wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of gold to his locks of his head, and no doubt but for hurting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he would haue forced his skul, and bowels within his breaſt to haue his load at full. So that you ſee the vnſatiableneſſe of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on gold, his heart is ſo ſet on it, and it ſo ſits on his heart, that there is no roome at all for any grace in the couetous mans heart; but euen as in the body, when the ſplene ſwelles, all other parts decay and conſume: ſo when the heart ſwelles with ouer great deſire of riches, all the graces of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and fade away. Wee ſee the hawthornes in the ſpring time haue faire white flowers, and pleaſant to the ſenſe, yet all the while it is but a pricking thorne, and he that catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth too haſtily to theſe flowers ſhal
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14574:26"/> pricke his hand: ſo are riches, ſaith Chriſt, though glorious to the eyes, <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 22.</note> yet but thornes to the couetous, they will prick both hand and hart, and the heart once wounded, the whole man will be conſumed. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for this was <hi>Iudas,</hi> who no doubt at firſt was a man of many good parts; he forſooke all to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his maſter Chriſt, preached the Goſpell, and wrought miracles as well as any of the reſt; but once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured with the flowring white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne of riches, and eagerly catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after it, his heart was pricked with the thorn that lay hid in theſe flowers, in ſuch ſort as that it ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and feſtred in him vnto death, bringing him vnto a moſt fearfull and dolefull downefall at the laſt. And good reaſon, for the couetous man is vniuſt againſt God, againſt man, againſt himſelfe, againſt his wealth. Againſt God; for hee doubteth and denieth his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and preferreth earthly traſh to God that ſhould be his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14574:27"/> treaſure. Againſt man his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in keeping all vnto himſelfe, whereas God hath made him but a ſteward, not a Lord thereof to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe vnto others. Yea he doth not onely keepe his owne from him, but by force as a Lion, and by fraud as a Fox, he wringeth and wreſteth his neighbours wealth to himſelfe; and therefore <hi>Syrake</hi> calleth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauder <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 11. 32. Iam. 5. 4.</note> of the poore, <hi>a man of blood.</hi> And S. <hi>Iames</hi> willeth ſuch cruell cormorants to weep and howle, for the hire of the labourers crieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He is vniuſt againſt himſelfe; for he doth euen ſell himſelfe to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell for wicked gaine, and like a ſumpter horſe, beareth burthens to the diuell all his life time, that in the end of his daies hee may bee thruſt into the dirty ſtable of hell, with a gald backe, and a wounded conſcience. Whereupon <hi>Syracides</hi> ſaith well, There is nothing worſe <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>luſ. 10. 9.</note> then a couetous man: why art thou proud O earth and aſhes? there is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14574:27"/> not a more wicked thing then to loue money, for ſuch an one would euen ſell his ſoule, and for his life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one is compelled to put out his owne bowels: agreeing with which is <hi>Salomon: He that is gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>of gaine, would take away the life of the owner thereof;</hi> and by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent his owne too, who muſt go for a recompence of his neighbors life.</p>
            <p>Finally, hee is vniuſt againſt his wealth; for hee hideth it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priues it of the end wherfore it was ordained, &amp; ſuffereth it to corrupt, and his garments to be motheaten, (as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith) and therfore no maruell if the wrath of God come vpon ſuch. And thus much for the foulneſſe of this ſinne of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe. Now I deſcend to the fourth circumſtance of my diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is, that no Miniſter, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with this ſinne, can deale ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely. My reaſons are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, euery Miniſter is, or ſhould be, the meſſenger of the Lord of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14574:28"/> hoſts: This heauenly Maſter, and earthly Mammon cannot be ſerued of one and the ſame ſeruant toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaith our Sauiour, for they are <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 24.</note> contrary one to the other: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Miniſter that is ouercome with couetouſneſſe, is fallen from Chriſt, as was ſeene in <hi>Iudas,</hi> &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be faithfull vnto him. Againe, <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 2.</note> the deceitfulneſſe of riches, and the cares of this world, choke the word (ſaith Chriſt). Hence I thus reaſon: where the word is choked, there the conſcience is clogged; where the conſcience is clogged, the heart is corrupted; where the heart is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, that man is not ſincere: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the couetous Preacher is an vnſincere Preacher. For euen as all beaſts, that go with their breaſts on the ground, were accounted abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable by the law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſo are <note place="margin">euit. 11. 42.</note> all thoſe, bee they Miniſters or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe hearts are as it were ſoddered vnto the earth. And here hence is it, that the diuell vſed this as the laſt, but not as the leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14574:28"/> to foyle Chriſt himſelfe, in tempting him, ſaying, <hi>All this will I giue thee:</hi> thinking with the Poet, <hi>Auri ſacra fames quid non?</hi> which certainly preuaileth much where grace gardeth not. Therefore wee reade, Reuel. 12. 4. That the diuell, the great Dragon, drew the third part of the ſtarres of heauen with his taile, and caſt them to the earth; and no maruell if hee thus ſtriue to preuaile: for if he once corrupt the ſhepheards, it is an eaſie matter to conſume the ſheepe. It is not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without good cauſe, that our Apoſtle doth ſo much ſtriue heere to cleare himſelfe of all coloured couetouſneſſe: for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he been co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, he could not be ſincere; for couetouſneſſe and corruption are alwaies companions, as was ſeene in <hi>Balaam,</hi> who louing the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſtiles <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 15.</note> it, though he proteſted, that if <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lak</hi> would giue him his houſe filled <note place="margin">Numb. 22. 18.</note> with gold and ſiluer, yet hee could not, nor would not ſpeake more
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14574:29"/> or leſſe then the Lord commanded him; yet for the loue of that wicked gaine he not only went, though firſt forbidden of the Lord, and after gaue wicked counſell to <hi>Balake</hi> (as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> reports) for his gaine. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joſephus Flauius.</note> 
               <hi>Antiquit. Iudaic. lib. 4. cap. 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe therfore of this doctrine is, firſt to teach vs, who are like to proue ſincere Preachers, and who not. The Scribes and Phariſies (ſaith Chriſt) deuoured widowes houſes, vnder a pretence of long prayer: theſe Phariſies haue their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers the Papiſts, who through coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe make merchandiſe of all that they doe. They ſell the vſe of time, of meates, and of mariages; they ſel their Maſſes and their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and their pardons, and purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and heauen it ſelfe; they make mony of <hi>Peter,</hi> and of <hi>Paul,</hi> of the Apoſtles, and of Martyrs, and of Chriſt himſelfe. Theſe no doubt are they of whom Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>through couetouſneſſe ſhall they with fained words make merchandiſe of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 3.</note>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:14574:29"/> 
               <hi>you:</hi> and therefore theſe men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in their doctrines bee ſincere. Come we vnto others, that through deſire of greatneſſe count gaine to bee godlineſſe, ioyning houſe vnto houſe, and Church vnto Church: if theſe ſhould appeale with our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to Gods record, I feare mee they would make their faults broad to their conſciences. And certainly doubt is to be taken of ſuch mens ſincerenes: for how ſhall they teach others to bee ſincere, that are not ſincere themſelues? Yet heere wee muſt take heede, that wee doe not count al to be couetous, that abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the vſe of earthly riches; for it is not the hauing of riches, but the truſting in riches that makes one couetous, as our Sauiour expounds <note place="margin">Mark. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccluſ. 13. 25.</note> it. Therfore ſaith <hi>Syrach, Riches are good to him that hath no ſinne.</hi> Elſe we ſhall condemne holy <hi>Abraham, Iob, Dauid, Salomon,</hi> and ſuch like, who were marueilous rich, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the worſe for their riches; whereas retchleſſe careleſneſſe and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14574:30"/> profuſe prodigalnes is a ſin againſt nature, for hee that ſhall not in an vpright and holy manner prouide for his owne, is worſe then an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell: <note place="margin">Tim 5.</note> yet we muſt not ſo truſt in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as that without theſe we mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt Gods prouidence and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. As pouertie therefore is euill in <note place="margin">cclus. 13 25.</note> the mouth of the vngodly, ſo riches is not euill in the heart ſanctified. Goods then with godlineſſe is no hindrance to ſincereneſſe; but mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfulnes with much or little ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, breeds neither ſoundneſſe nor ſincerenes.</p>
            <p>A ſecond vſe is, that ſuch people as in their owne knowledge and conſciences, perceiue their Paſtors to be faithfull and freeſt off coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, theſe ſhould giue great credit to their doctrines for ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. In the eleuenth of the Acts it is recorded, that when the Church vnderſtood, that a great number at Antiochia beleeued and turned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, they ſent <hi>Barnabas</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; who when hee was come
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14574:30"/> and had ſeene the grace of God, in the ſincereneſſe of his heart, he was glad (ſaith the text) and exhorted all that with purpoſe of heart they would cleaue vnto the Lord, Where the holy Ghoſt ſheweth, that his ſo holy exhortation had a great and a bleſſed effect, for much people ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues vnto the Lord. And what was the cauſe that ſhould moue this people thus to ioyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord? it is there noted, that he was a good man and full of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Act. 11. 24</note> Ghoſt. As if hee ſhould ſay, his goodneſſe and ſincereneſſe was of great force to moue them to turne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. So we reade of <hi>Herod,</hi> though otherwiſe a proud Prince and prophane, yet when hee heard <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> hee did many things, <note place="margin">Mark. 6. 20. 21.</note> and heard him gladly. And what was the cauſe that ſhould moue him hereunto? the holie Ghoſt noteth the cauſe, that it was <hi>Iohus</hi> ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For <hi>Herod</hi> feared <hi>Iohn,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that hee was a iuſt man and an holy, and reuerenced him: ſo that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14574:31"/> thoſe that will not reuerence their ſincere Preacher, are more proſane then wicked <hi>Herod</hi> was. And yet behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proteruitie of theſe times, wherein all for the moſt part hate to be reproued, becauſe they haue no hearts to be reformed, who like the peruerſe Galathians, count him <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 16.</note> their enemie that tels the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth. The reaſon whereof our Sauiour yeelds, namely, that hee that euill <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 20.</note> doth, hateth the light, neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the light, leſt his deedes ſhould bee reproued. So that the moſt profound are eſteemed the moſt profane, euen monſtrous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Zach. 3. 8. as ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Iſai. 8. 18. the moſt conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thought to bee moſt conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, Ierem. 15. 20. But what doth this bewray, but that the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is dangerouſly ſicke, and out of order? euen as a man in a feuer, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gall hath diſperſed it ſelfe ouer the ſtomacke, findes no good taſte or reliſh of the beſt meates: and as the ſluggiſh ſleeper in the lethergie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14574:31"/> holds him his greateſt foe that is his beſt friend, in awaking him; ſo it fareth with thoſe poore ſoules, that are moſt ſicke with ſinne, they would goe to perdition in peace, and cannot abide to be rouſed out of their ſinnes. Therefore wee haue great cauſe to pray with <hi>Dauid</hi> to eſtabliſh vs with right and free ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that being ſpirituall we may be able to diſcerne all things as they are; we may loue ſoundly them that deale ſincerely, and haue them in <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. 13.</note> ſingular regard for their workes ſake.</p>
            <p>Finally, ſeeing that couetouſnes is ſo great, ſo groſſe, and ſo generall a ſinne, let euery man betimes exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his own ſoule, whether it haue taken any hold in his heart: for (aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelues) their liues are miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and their ends damnable, (as <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 19</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) that liue and dye in this ſinne. And therefore ſeeing the danger is ſo great, and yet the ſinne ſo common, neede haue we (euerie one of vs) to pray to God with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:14574:32"/> to encline our hearts vnto his <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 36.</note> teſtimonies, and not to couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Which that wee may doe, wee muſt labour to get that bleſſed gift of contentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the holy Ghoſt <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 5</note> exhorteth vnto, ſaying, <hi>Let not your conuerſation be in couetouſnes, but be content with that you haue: for hee hath ſaid, I wil not faile thee, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee.</hi> A notable example of this vertue we haue in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who had learned in whatſoeuer ſtate hee was, therewith to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 11. 12.</note> and therefore he ſaith, <hi>I can be abaſed, and I can abound: euerie where and in all things I am instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, both to be full, and to be hungry, to abound, and to haue want.</hi> This which <hi>Paul</hi> practiſed is ſoone ſaid, but not ſo ſoone done. That wee therefore may after his example be content in euery ſtate of life, and ſhunne this foule ſinne of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, let vs conſider of theſe preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiues. Firſt ſet before our eyes the commandement of God that ſaith, Thou ſhalt not couet, not thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14574:32"/> houſe only, but not any thing that is his. For looke what is ſinne to take in the ſight of man, is ſinne to wiſh in the eyes of God; but in mans ſight, it is ſin to take any thing that is thy neighbours, for it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of nature, that wils thee to doe as thou wouldeſt bee done vnto; and againſt the law of iuſtice, that commandeth to giue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man his due: Therefore (ſaith God) thou ſhalt not couet any thing that is thy neighbours, be it neuer ſo little, it is too much to couet; and though hee can ſpare it, God will not ſpare thee for wiſhing it: and though it bee not much wherein thou offend'ſt, yet the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God is great, whom herein thou offend'ſt: therefore thou ſeeſt there is no warrant at al, to couet.</p>
            <p>Againe, conſider that though a man haue that which hee doth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet it cannot profit him, vnleſſe God bleſſe it. The Iſraelites (ſaith <hi>Dauid)</hi> coueted fleſh for their luſts, and God gaue them their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14574:33"/> with their deſire he gaue them fleſh, but hee ſent leanneſſe withall <note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 15</note> into their ſoules: ſo, many are ſicke with <hi>Ahabs</hi> diſeaſe, propoſing to themſelues if I had ſuch a dwelling, then I ſhould haue content; if ſuch a liuing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhould haue no want. But conſider, I pray you, may not this be a fond and falſe perſwaſion? may not God croſſe thee in thy wiſhed-for dwelling, with vnwiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for diſeaſes in thy body, and with torturing horrour in thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? and then thy dwelling will not delight thee, and thy couering will not content thee. And as for riches, thou maiſt drinke in gold with <hi>Balthazar,</hi> and ſee with him <note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> thy doome and downfull grauen in the walles of thy palaces, that may more quaile thee, then thy gold and wine can comfort thee. Therefore <hi>Dauids</hi> counſell is worthy, Pſal. 62. 10. 11. where he aduiſeth, ſaying, <hi>If riches encreaſe, ſet not thine heart vpon them.</hi> Why? for three reaſons: firſt, for <hi>God ſpake once or twice, and</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:14574:33"/> 
               <hi>I heard it, that power belongeth to God.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, Nothing hath any power to do a man good, but only God. Secondly, <hi>to thee, O Lord, belongeth mercie:</hi> noting, that nothing procureth pitie and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, but onely God: and that a man is loued and kindly entreated, it is not from his wealth, but from God that puts loue into mens hearts. Thirdly, <hi>thou Lord rewardeſt euery man according to his worke:</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that God lookes to our works, not to our wealth; when hee comes to iudgement, ſinne then ſhall haue ſhame, and ſinceritie ſaluation; whatſoeuer our wealth hath been, riches deliuer not in the day of the Lords wrath, but righteouſnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth from death: riches then cannot helpe, why therefore ſhould we ſo much couet them?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider how little will conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nature; we brought nothing with vs into the world, and we ſhall carrie nothing out. If therefore we haue <hi>Iacobs</hi> wiſh, food and raiment,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14574:34"/> let vs therewith be content. Nay, we haue warrant to craue no more then <hi>Agur</hi> craued; <hi>Feede me with food conuenient for me,</hi> Prou. 30. 8. therefore our Sauiour taught vs to pray on this manner, <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread:</hi> that is, bread for our ſubſtances; or ſuch bread as is ſufficient to preſerue our liues, And that God is diſpleaſed at mens ouer greedie crauing much, hee would haue vs to learne by his allowance in the wilderneſſe, for there hee fed his children from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah <note place="margin">Exod. 16. 20</note> ſufficient for the day; and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in greedineſſe would bring in more, he cauſed it to putrifie and to be full of wormes: to teach vs, that he accurſeth al that we craue, more then he alloweth vs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, conſider that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we haue, if but meane fare, if but poore rags, but a ruinous cottage, yet it is farre better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we deſerue; bread or water is too good for the beſt of vs: our ſinnes can challenge nothing but ſackcloth to couer vs,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14574:34"/> and if we had our deſert, our houſes ſhould be hell. And therefore ſtriue to haue a ſenſe and feeling of the want of Chriſt, and to ſee our dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable eſtate in our ſelues without him; and then, though a man were couetouſneſſe it ſelfe, this will be a meanes to turne his heart from the pelfe of this world, and to ſeeke wholly after ſpirituall and heauenly things. For the conſideration of our owne miſerie in our ſelues, and a liuely ſenſe of the need we haue of Chriſt, will make vs hunger after him and his righteouſneſſe aboue all things in the world. We finde by experience, that many are endued with good gifts of knowledge, of ioy in the Word, of zeale in good things, &amp;c. who neuertheleſſe in their callings are ouercome with this foule ſinne of couetouſneſſe: and the reaſon is, becauſe they were neuer throughly touched with any ſenſe or feeling of their neede they had of Chriſt: and therefore they neuer thought with S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14574:35"/> 
               <hi>Quid prodeſt, ſi omnia habes, eum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men qui omnia dedit non habere?</hi> What profit is it to haue all things, and to want the giuer of all things, without whom all poſſeſſions and poſſeſſors are vile and miſerable? The conſideration whereof made <hi>Moſes</hi> (when he came to yeeres) to <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 11. 26.</note> entertaine affliction, <hi>eſteeming the rebuke of Chriſt greater riches, then the treaſures of Egypt:</hi> becauſe hee had reſpect to the recompence of reward. So, did wee (beloued) ſee out vileneſſe without Chriſt, and made once to hunger after him, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery one would begin to ſay with S. <hi>Paul, I eſteeme all things as dung,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hil. 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>in regard of Chriſt:</hi> and with <hi>Dauid, As the Hart brayeth after the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 42. 1.</note> 
               <hi>of waters, ſo thirſteth my ſoule after thee, O Lord.</hi> This is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Chriſt, <hi>Firſt ſeeke the kingdom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 6. 33</note> 
               <hi>of God and his righteouſneſſe.</hi> Wee muſt in our ſelues bee as the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man, that lay in the way, that Chriſt Ieſus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Samaritane may come by vs to ſupple our wounds,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14574:35"/> and to poure his owne pretious blood into our ſoules; for as <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid, <hi>God filleth the hungry with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 53</note> 
               <hi>good things, but the rich hee ſends empty away.</hi> Thus you ſee that the feeling of the want of ſpirituall grace, makes men contemne, or to ſet light of earthly riches.</p>
            <p>Finally, conſider the ſpecial, wiſe and fatherly prouidence of God, in diſpoſing and gouerning the things of the world, hee hath riches e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in his hand for all: If then it doe not ſeeme good to his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to giue thee more or better things; know aſſuredly, that that is beſt for thee, who can chuſe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for thee, then thou for thy ſelfe; for hee is a moſt wiſe caruer, and <note place="margin">Pſa. 34. 10.</note> faithfull Creator, and can denie no good thing to them that feare him: the conſideration whereof made holy <hi>Iob</hi> to praiſe God in wealth and woe, ſaying, <hi>The Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 1. 22.</note> 
               <hi>hath giuen, and the Lord hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> comforted himſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14574:36"/> this ſpeciall prouidence of God, acknowledging, that the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſhepheard hee ſhould want <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 23. 1.</note> nothing; and therefore finding this Lord to be the portion of his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, and of his cup: he was ſure hee would maintaine his lot; and confeſſeth that the lines are fallen <note place="margin">ſalm. 16. 5. 6.</note> vnto him in pleaſant places; yea, that he had a faire heritage. Thus, if with <hi>Dauid,</hi> any one can once make the Lord his portion, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but bee full of contentation. For how can he want any thing, that hath for his portion the Lord, the guider and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all things?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14574:36"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. THES. 2. 5.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Neither ſought we praiſe of men, nor of you, nor of any others.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is the third fault, which the Apoſtle laboureth to remoue from himſelfe, to proue his ſincerenes by; namely ambition, either for praiſe or profit; of which he labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to cleare himſelfe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quels, by his, and his fellowes, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; and aſſures himſelfe, that if he can free himſelfe and them from this and the two former vices, that he ſhall ſufficiently confirme his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion of their ſincereneſſe, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14574:37"/> in doctrine, but alſo in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof.</p>
            <p>In handling of which fault of Ambition, I will obſerue the ſame order that I did in the former two, of Adulation and Auarice. For I will follow theſe foure circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I will firſt ſhew what Ambition is. 2. How manifold, and what are the parts of it. 3. How foule and dangerous a ſinne it is. And 4. that the Miniſter that is ambitious, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deale ſincerely in his doctrines: and finally theſe heads being han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, I will draw out ſome vſe that we are to make of it, and ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies thereof.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, what Ambition is, our Apoſtle ſaith in my text, <hi>wee ſought not praiſe of men, nor of you, nor of any other.</hi> Where our Apoſtle ſeemes to import, that ouer-greedy ſeeking, &amp; an ouer-griple deſire of the praiſe of men, is Ambition; and ſo doe the very words themſelues in the Originall ſignifie, if wee well conſider them; for Ambition is a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14574:37"/> Latine word, deriued of the verbe <hi>Ambire,</hi> which is, to goe about, to ſue, ſeeke, and keepe a quoile in the world for praiſe and promotion; to which the Greeke word φιλοτιμία agreeth, which ſignifieth ouer great loue of honour, and greedie deſire of glory. Whence (I thinke) I may thus define Ambition, <hi>viz. Ambition is a baſe ſinne, whereby a man is ſo carried away with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate deſire of his owne praiſe and honour, that whether he deſerue it or no, he regards it more then Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or his neighbours good.</hi> Which definition being compared with her parts or cauſes, will (I geſſe) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be an abſolute definition; her parts I make to bee her Kinde and Difference; her kind is, that it is a ſinne, or baſe ſinne, her diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from other ſinnes is, that it makes a man ſicke with ſelfe loue: For the kinde, that it is a baſe ſinne, I proue by reaſons natural, politick, and diuine. Naturall reaſon proues it, For whereas man by nature is a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14574:38"/> ſociable creature of the ſame matter and mould, forme and faſhion with others, &amp; therfore ſhould affect and delight in &amp; with others; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp with ſelf-loue, &amp; with a deſire of his own praiſe &amp; preferment, that he becomes a <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> a <hi>Miſanthropos,</hi> a deſpiſer and hater of all others in reſpect of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <note place="margin">Tullij of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. lib. 3.</note> Whereupon Heathen <hi>Tullie</hi> could ſay by the light of nature, that in a free City nothing can bee imagined more foule or mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous, then the ambitious deſire of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. To which accordeth diuine <hi>Ierome,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Vilium est hominum alios viles facere, &amp; qui ſuo merito placere non poteſt, placere velle alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum comparatione:</hi> that is, it is the property of vile and baſe men to diſgrace others, to be graced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (as all ambitious men ſeeke to doe) and hauing no merit of his owne by compariſon, to ſeeke to be accounted of by others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that this is a baſe ſin, croſſing pollicy, I proue; for it ſeeks
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14574:38"/> the downfall of all humane ſociety. For wheras one ſtriues to be aboue another, there is nothing but enuie and deſtruction of one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <note place="margin">Epiſt. 2. Lib. 12.</note> whereupon <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith well, Take heed of Ambition, it is a vaine ſwelling, and turbulent euill that hath none end, and vexeth himſelfe as much to ſee another before him, as himſelfe to bee behind another; ſo that it is carried with a double enuie: <hi>vides autem quám miſer, ſi is cui inuidetur &amp; inuidet:</hi> behold then(ſaith hee) how miſerable the Ambitious man is, if hee enuic him that is enuied by him? which thing <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 10.</note> made wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> to affirme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>only by pride doth man ſtir vp contention, but with the well aduiſed is wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diuine reaſon proues ambition to be a baſe ſinne; for whereas God hath reſerued theſe three things to himſelfe, <hi>viz.</hi> Vengeance, Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Honour; the diuell by this ſinne of Ambition, ſtriuing to bee equall with God, of an Angell of light, became a ſpirit of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14574:39"/> whereupon <hi>Baſilius magnus</hi> calles it the diuels diſeaſe, becauſe it makes men like the diuell; for the ambitious man hath no beleefe, as our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>How can yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 44.</note> 
               <hi>that receiue honour one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſeeke not the honour that commeth of God alone?</hi> So that you ſee proued by reaſons naturall, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and diuine, this <hi>genus,</hi> or kind of my definition, that Ambition is a baſe ſinne.</p>
            <p>The difference of this ſin from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is, that this ſinne makes one to be ſicke of ſelfe-loue, euen with an inordinate deſire of his owne praiſe and honour; ſo that, as <hi>Icarus,</hi> hee would mount aboue the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines: for whereas the couetous man deſireth riches, and the flarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer bellie-cheere and maintenance, the Ambitious man aimes onely at honours; ſo that hee regards not friend, brother, nor father; but with <hi>Abſolon,</hi> will ſeeke his fathers head, to haue his crowne.</p>
            <p>Hence we may deſcend to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14574:39"/> the cauſes both efficient, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, formall, and finall of this ſoule ſinne; the opening of which will make vs further and fuller to behold the vglineſſe of this baſe monſter.</p>
            <p>The efficient cauſe of Ambition, is ignorance: for howſoeuer ſome thinke, that pride was the cauſe of the fall of men and Angels, though it be not denied but that pride was in this ſinne, yet the breeder of this pride was follie, which made them proud; therefore <hi>Iob</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>found follie in the Angels:</hi> ſo that ignorance being the mother of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, is the firſt cauſe of the pride and Ambition of Angels and men; and good reaſon, for no man knowing God or himſelfe as he ought, can be proud: ſo that one may be bold to ſay to the Ambitious, That folly was his mother, and ſhame will be his daughter.</p>
            <p>The materiall cauſe of Ambition is, vaine praiſe and honour, which ſo bewitcheth the heart of the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14574:40"/> as that their whole man is ſet vpon it, as S. <hi>Bernard, in lib. 3. de conſideratione</hi> affirmeth, ſaying <hi>O ambitio ambientium crux? quomodo omnes torques? omnibus places? nil acerbius cruciat, nil moleſtius inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etat, nil tamen apud miſeros morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les crebrius negotijs eius:</hi> that is, O Ambition, the croſſe of the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, how doſt thou torment all, and yet pleaſe all? nothing doth more cruelly crucifie, nothing doth more trouble ſomly vex men, and yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more common with miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mortall men then her affaires. Act. 12, 23. We may ſee, that <hi>Herod Agrippa,</hi> to win honour of men, vſurped to himſelfe the honour of God, &amp; for it God made him more baſe then a worme.</p>
            <p>The formall cauſe thereof is, an ouer greedy and inordinate deſire of honour, ſuch as was ſeene in <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> who being ambitious of a Monarchie, ſhamed not to vtter the words of <hi>Euripides, Sipeieran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum est, regnandi cauſa peierandum</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:14574:40"/> 
               <hi>est:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, Sweare, and forſweare for a Kingdome: for the getting of honors, forget God, kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and conſcience: ſo that the end of Ambition is alſo to preferre his owne honors before Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or neighbors good; as was ſeene in <hi>Herod,</hi> but ſpecially in <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 12.</note> who to vphold his owne honour, ſet vp Idols in <hi>Bethel,</hi> and <hi>Dan;</hi> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leſt if his ſubiects ſhould goe vp to Ieruſalem, to the place of Gods worſhip, the hearts of the people ſhould turne againe vnto <note place="margin">1. King. 12. 27.</note> the Lord, and to <hi>Rehoboam</hi> King of Iuda; and ſo he preferred his owne honour to the honour of God, and the ſaluation of his people, ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and horrible is this ſin of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, whoſe kind is (as you haue heard) a baſe ſinne, whoſe property is, too great a deſire of honour; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie is her mother, and ſhame her daughter; her matter, honour; and forme, too great a deſire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and her end brings contempt of God &amp; man, to commend her ſelfe.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14574:41"/> Thus we reade that <hi>Abimelecke</hi> ſlue <note place="margin">Iudg. 9. 5. Matth. 2. 2. Sam. 15</note> his owne brethren; <hi>Herod</hi> killed his owne ſonne, &amp; <hi>Abſolon</hi> would haue ſlaine his owne father for a kingdome and for honour.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore in the ſecond place conſider the parts and litter of this monſter; for this cur'ſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wants not her accurſed daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; I will therefore obſerue for her parts theſe foure, <hi>viz.</hi> Self-loue, Forgetfulneſſe, A ſingular opinion, and Furie.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, that Selfe-loue is Ambitions daughter, or at leaſt her ſiſter, will eaſily appeare; for a mans ſeeking for honor, at length brings him to bee ſo greatly in loue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as that in compariſon thereof he deſpiſeth al others, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 17</note> ſpeaketh of the falſe teachers, <hi>They would exclude you</hi> (meaning from vs) <hi>that yee might altogether loue them.</hi> So there are too many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs in theſe daies, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing Satans kingdome to begin to be weakened, and the <hi>Dagon</hi> of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14574:41"/> ſuperſtition to begin to fall downe, by the faithfull labours of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: yet becauſe this was not done by them and their aduice, that they might haue the praiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof; therefore meerely through ſelfe-loue they ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt theſe good procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and by theſe meanes vphold ſtill Antichriſts kingdome, and ſo become authours of diuiſion and confuſion; as S. <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith, <hi>theſe are makers of ſects:</hi> whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V. 19. 1. Tim. 4 2. and 4.</note> therefore tearmes <hi>louers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,</hi> and <hi>louers of pleaſure more then louers of God.</hi> This is one Cub of this curſed litter.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Cub is Forgetfulneſſe; for a mans ouer-weening deſire of getting honours to himſelfe, makes him vtterly forgetfull of God, of himſelfe, of others: for euen as the ſtomacke ouer-ſtuft with winde, is apt to receiue no nouriſhing meate, vntill it haue vent for that winde; ſo the Ambitious man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer-ſtuft with pride, hath no
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14574:42"/> roome in his heart all this while for the knowledge of God, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or other; which knowledge of God, &amp;c. if it had once entred into his heart, it would preſently make him to fall from his pride; for it would tel him, that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure the children of pride, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith: and that <hi>God reſisteth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 41. 25</note> 
               <hi>the proud, but giueth grace to the humble and meeke,</hi> as <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith; <note place="margin">Iam. 4. 6.</note> &amp; therefore that <hi>pride goeth before deſtruction, and a high mind before</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 10.</note> 
               <hi>the fall,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith. Alſo, that <hi>the pride of man ſhall bring him low,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 23.</note> 
               <hi>but the humble in ſpirit ſhall enioy glory,</hi> as he elſewhere ſaith. So that it is not without good cauſe affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that <hi>è coelo deſcendit Noſce te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum. i.</hi> It is a ſpeciall gift from heauen, for a man to know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Whence I conclude, that where Ambition is, there ignorance of God and himſelf is.</p>
            <p>The third Cub of this litter, is a ſingular opinion of himſelfe: which makes the ambitious man ſay to his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14574:42"/> brethren, in compariſon of himſelf, Stand there, or ſit heere vnder my <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 3.</note> footſtoole, as <hi>Iames</hi> reporteth. To which height of pride, that proud Prelate and Antichriſt of Rome by his ambition hath aſpired, making Emperours his ſtirrop-holders, and Kings (as did <hi>Adonibezek,</hi> Iudg. 1. 7.) his footſtoole: of ſuch S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iſti tantam ſibi aſſumunt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem, vt ſiuè dextra docent ſiuè ſiniſtra, ſiuè bona, ſiuè mala, nolint diſcipulos ratione diſcutere:</hi> Theſe aſſume to themſelues (ſaith <hi>Ierome)</hi> ſo great authoritie, that whether they teach truth or falſehood, good or euill, their hearers may not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into it by reaſon. And of ſuch the Prophet <hi>Habakuk</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>the proud man is as he that tranſgreſſeth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>by wine: therefore ſhall hee not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Whelp of this litter is Fury, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Only by pride doth man make contention,</hi> as may <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 10</note> be ſeene in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who in his ambitious humour was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14574:43"/> to haue his image to be ſet vp, and adored, who hearing that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drak, Meſhak</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> would not feede his proud fancie, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue of his profane pride, brake out into furie and rage, ſaying, <hi>What diſorder, &amp;c.</hi> and when they vtterly refuſed to adore his image, then was <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> full of rage, ſaith <note place="margin">Dan. 3. 19</note> the text. So that the ambitious man is for his furie like a mad man, and therefore not worthie to bee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a man.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the parts of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how deformed they are: Now I will deſcend to the third part of my diuiſion, to ſhew how foule this ſinne is; and it is ſo ſoule a ſinne, as that <hi>Timon</hi> makes this ſinne, as the Apoſtle doth couetouſneſſe, to bee the roote of all euill. S. <hi>Baſil</hi> calles it the Diuels diſeaſe, becauſe it firſt diſeaſed diuell and man; for <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> and <hi>Adams</hi> ambition to bee as high as God, made them to be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to all other creatures. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Syrak</hi> ſaith, <hi>That it is the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 10. 14.</note>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:14574:43"/> 
               <hi>of ſinne, and hee that hath it, ſhall poure out abomination, and at length be ouerthrowne.</hi> Therefore S. <hi>Bernard</hi> termes <hi>Ambition a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till euill, a ſecret poyſon, an hidden plague, the miſtris of deceit, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of hypocriſie, the father of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe, the originall of vices, the food of faults, the ruſt of vertues, the moth of holineſſe, the blinder of the heart, making diſeaſes out of reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and begetting faintneſſe out of medicines.</hi> And to this end S. <hi>Baſil</hi> alleaging Chriſts ſaying of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that giue, faſt, and pray, to bee ſeene of men, that they haue their reward, willeth all men to take heed of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, which is (ſaith he) <hi>the ſweete ſpoyler of all ſpirituall gifts, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſome enemie of our ſoules, the moth of al vertues, and the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant betrayer of all happineſſe.</hi> All which wee may ſee moſt fully veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the penners of the Tripertite Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie write at large in the ſixth booke thereof, ſhewing that <hi>Iulian</hi> at the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14574:44"/> firſt being an Emperour of many good parts, after that the Syren ſongs of flatterers had blowne vp his heart with Ambition, he was ſo violently carried away with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of glorie and honour, that hee vaunted that hee would match <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the Great; yea hee was ſo beſotted with that humour, as that hee fained that <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſoule was fleeted into his bodie; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the multitude to hate the Chriſtians, hee ſet himſelfe againſt them to winne popular applauſe, vaunting that he would pull down Chriſt the Galileian from heauen, and ſo held on till God from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen cauſed a dart to ſtab him to the heart. So that you may ſee in <hi>Iulian</hi> the viue picture of Ambition, and withall a preſident in him of Gods fierce wrath againſt this baſe ſinne, bringing him to a moſt ſhameful &amp; fearful end &amp; deſtruction. Al which being ſo appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, together with the crueltie that the ambitious practiſe, not ſparing friend, brother, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14574:44"/> as you haue heard, you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the foulnes and ouglineſſe of this ſinne: which being ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly proued, I come to the fourth part of my diuiſion, that is, that the Ambitious Miniſter cannot be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. My reaſons to proue this are theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, euery ambitious man is an hypocrite, for he doth al to be ſeene of men: where hypocriſie is, there can be no ſincerenes, as our Sauiour proues at large, Matth. 23. therefore a Miniſter ambitious, cannot be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere.</p>
            <p>Secondly, continuing in his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition hee is an heretike: for what more palpable hereſie can there be, then to glorie in his owne gifts and honours? <hi>What haſt thou that thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> 
               <hi>haſt not receiued?</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul:</hi> ſo that for a man to glorie in his owne gifts, is to race out the foundation, that <hi>euery good and perfect gift com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from God.</hi> So to glorie in a <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 17</note> mans own merits, is to deny Chriſts merits; and to glorie in his owne
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14574:45"/> wit and freewill, is to denie the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt to bee his guider; and to ſeeke only his owne praiſe, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the communion of Saints: which being ſo, he is an heretike, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be ſincere.</p>
            <p>My third reaſon is, that the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious man is a theefe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be ſincere. The ground of this reaſon is the Maxime of Chriſt; <hi>He that ſpeaketh of himſelfe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">oh. 7. 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeketh his owne glorie: but hee that ſeeketh his glorie that ſent him, the ſame is true, and no vnrighteouſneſſe is in him.</hi> Whence I thus reaſon: Euery ſincere Miniſter is bound to ſeeke Gods glorie that ſent him, and not his owne glorie; elſe hee is not true nor ſincere, but a theefe and a rob-god: but euery ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Miniſter ſeeketh not Gods glorie, but his owne: therefore he is not true, but a rob-god, and by a conſequent vnſincere. That euery ambitious Miniſter ſeeketh not Gods glorie but his owne, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the former part of Chriſts
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14574:45"/> aſſertion, for hee ſpeaketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: therefore he ſeeketh his owne glorie, therefore not Gods, for theſe are oppoſite: and for this cauſe our Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was willing to bee baſe, that God might be honorable: yea he had a deſire to haue his name raced out of the booke of life, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Gods glorie ſhould bee obſcured; and for this cauſe did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hazard his owne life and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to vphold Gods glorie: whence I may boldly collect, that for any Miniſter to ſeeke in his miniſterie his owne praiſe and honour, and for the getting thereof to neglect Gods praiſe and honour, is to be a theefe and rob-god, and therefore ſuch an one cannot bee ſincere. Hence then you may ſee the force of our Apoſtles reaſons: <hi>Wee haue not vſed in our doctrines flattering words, nor coloured couetouſneſſe, nor ſought praiſe of men:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our doctrines are ſincere and ſound. If ſo, then you ought to bee conſtant followers of thoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14574:46"/> which haue bin taught with ſuch ſincereneſſe.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this doctrine is, to teach all in generall (but ſpecially Miniſters of Gods word) to take heed of this ſin of Ambition, which is ſo foule a ſinne, as that it makes them that haue it ſicke of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels diſeaſe, &amp; will in the end bring them to the Diuels diſtreſſe, to bee caſt out of heauen and happineſſe, without ſpeedie repentance: for it makes them proue hypocrites, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and ſacrilegious the eues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God that ſends them: and therefore God that makes not the wicked innocent, will not, nor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Iod. 34. 7.</note> leaue them vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out amendment. It was the rule of our Apoſtle, <hi>Whether yee eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer yee doe, doe all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cor. 10 31.</note> 
               <hi>to the glorie of God.</hi> It was our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Abſit, <hi>God forbid that I ſhould reioyce, but in the croſſe of Chriſt:</hi> and therefore our reioycing ſhould be in the Lord, and for the Lord, to his praiſe and glory. And thus ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14574:46"/> our owne honour for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, God will make grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honour to follow vs, as the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow followeth the bodie; for his promiſe is paſt vnreuocable, <hi>thoſe that honour me, I will honour.</hi> When God bid <hi>Moſes</hi> to goe on his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to <hi>Pharaoh, Moſes</hi> being pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie <note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note> to his owne wants, in humilitie deſired God to ſend another. But we wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not now ſtore of ambitious <note place="margin">Numb. 1</note> 
               <hi>Corahs,</hi> that will be ready enough to ſtep vp in <hi>Moſes</hi> place, and to ſit downe in his chaire too, without bidding or ſending at all. Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Simon Peter</hi> and his fellowes, <note place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Freely ye haue receiued, freely giue: but now ambition makes many a <hi>Simon Magus</hi> to giue for reward, before hee receiue of free gift. So that two ſuch monſters meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, as <hi>Simon</hi> ſpeaks of, to wit, πλεοτεξία and φιλοδοξια, Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and Ambition, they haue almoſt ouerturned all zeale and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for where ſoeuer theſe raigne, religion goes to ruine; as may bee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14574:47"/> ſeene in that Antichriſtian darknes of Rome, that for ambitious deſire of raigning, haue ſet all things to ſale: they ſell Sacraments and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Purgatorie, and pardons, and Maſſes, and merits, &amp;c. So that one may marueile, that they vaunt that they ſucceede <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> their deeds pleading ſo openly that they ſucceed <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> And I wiſh that amongſt vs Profeſſors, this treaſonable ſinne had no trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; which for the ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of gaine, and greatneſſe in the Church-ſellers, and of honours in the Church-buyers, haue eaten vp <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſai. 3. 14.</note> the Lords vineyard, and the ſpoile of the poore is in their houſes: but the Lord will enter into iudgement with them, ſaith <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> Seeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that this ſinne is ſo great and grieuous, it ſtands euery man in hand to ſtriue againſt it, and in the feare of God to deſire his aſſiſtance, that wee all may be kept free from this ſinne ſo dangerous. The reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies whereof are theſe: firſt, the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14574:47"/> feare of God: for the <hi>eye of the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 33. 18. 19.</note> 
               <hi>is vpon them that feare him, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their ſoules from death, and to preſerue them in the time of dearth.</hi> Therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> exhorteth the Saints to feare the Lord: His reaſon is, <hi>for nothing wanteth to them that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 9. 10</note> 
               <hi>feare him. The lions doe lacke, and ſuffer hunger: but they which ſeeke the Lord, ſhall want nothing that is good.</hi> It was <hi>Daniels</hi> experience of Gods promiſe, when he was ſhut vp in the lions denne in Babylon, and had now faſted three daies, when God ſent <hi>Habakkuk</hi> to him with his prouiſion, which hee had made for <note place="margin">Dan. 14. 37. 38.</note> his reapers, and cried to him, <hi>O Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, Daniel, take thy dinner that God hath ſent thee: Then ſaid Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, O God, thou haſt thought vpon me, and thou neuer faileſt them that ſeeke thee, and loue thee.</hi> And indeed it is the faithfulnes of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>I will not faile thee, nor forſake</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioſua. 1. 5 Heb. 13. 5</note> 
               <hi>thee;</hi> and his moſt wiſe prouidence, that made meate before hee made man; he cannot forſake the worke <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 2 25. 26.</note>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:14574:48"/> of his owne hand; but he that hath giuen vs his ſonne, will with him giue vs all things alſo: he that hath prepared a kingdome for his, will not faile to furniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with things neceſſary to bring them to that kingdome. Therefore following the counſell of Saint <hi>Peter, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 4. 19.</note> 
               <hi>your ſelues to him in al diſtreſſe, in well doing, as vnto a faithful Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond remedie is godlines, which hath the promiſe of the life <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 8.</note> that now is, and of that which is to come; and therefore godlineſſe is <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 6.</note> great gaine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with the vſe of his ſufficiency, ſaith <hi>Tremelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi> or with approuing of his lot, ſaith <hi>Arias Montanus,</hi> whereby the holy Ghoſt would teach, that the godly mans lot is God himſelfe, &amp; therefore hee hath a goodly heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, <note place="margin">ſal. 16. 6.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith; for how can hee want goods, that hath God, the authour of all goodneſſe? how can he want treaſure, that hath the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it ſelfe?</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:14574:48"/>
            <p>Thirdly, therefore we ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the counſell of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Firſt ſeeke the kingdome of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 33</note> 
               <hi>God and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and then all other things</hi> (bee it wealth, or worth, or honour) <hi>ſhall be caſt vpon vs. Dauid</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>will not famiſh the ſoule of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> and <hi>hee neuer ſaw the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous forſaken, or their ſeed to beg their bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, God hath promiſed to <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2 30</note> honour them that honour him, but hee reiecteth the proud, putting <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> downe the mighty from their ſeat, and exalteth the humble and meek: as <hi>Adam</hi> when he would be cheek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with God, brought both him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his poſterity to a ſtale, plunging himſelfe and them into deſtruction and perdition; but <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> that was deſpiſed in the ſight of <note place="margin">2. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Michal,</hi> for his humbling himſelfe before God, was by God taken from the ewes great with young, to feed his people in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance <note place="margin">Pſa. 78.</note> in Iſrael.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14574:49"/>
            <p>Fifthly, he that is a ſeruant in his fathers houſe, ſhall bee prouided with things conuenient; for God will withhold no good thing from him that leadeth a godly life.</p>
            <p>Finally, hee is a very ambitious rob-God, that is deſirous to take that commendation to himſelfe, that is appropriated onely to the Lord; therefore let all walke hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly before God, and ſurely in due time they ſhall be exalted.</p>
            <p>To conclude this text, it is nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the Apoſtle ſaith here, <hi>that he ſought not praiſe,</hi> which is to be vnderſtood, that he ſought it not in the firſt place, or chiefly; elſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour followeth the honorable, as the ſhadow the body, and <hi>bones est virtutis praemium,</hi> honour is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of vertue. Secondly, he ſought not honour by ſiniſter and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means; but by cauſing his light to ſhine before men, he made them by ſeeing his good workes to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, in ſo doing, he could not want his owne glory too; for God
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14574:49"/> will honour them that honour 1. him; and the people are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 30. 1. Theſſ. 5. 12., 13.</note> to know them, that are ouer them in the Lord, and admoniſh them, and to haue them in ſingular loue for their workes ſake. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he doth not ſay, We receiued not praiſe, but, We, ſought it not. The dutie then of the people is, to giue to euery man his due, <hi>honour,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13., 7.</note> 
               <hi>to whom ye owe honour,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith. For this cauſe the younger are commanded to honor the elder, and the elder that ruleth well, is worthie of double honour; and this is both iuſt and profitable. Iuſt, becauſe wee muſt doe good to them that doe good to vs, elſe wee ſhall be vnthankful, and worſe then ſinners, and there is not a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable duite, then to giue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to whom it is due; therefore it is iuſt to honour our teachers. It is alſo profitable, as well to our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors, as to our ſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. To them, for hereby they are encouraged to do their worke with
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14574:50"/> ioy, and not with griefe: to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <note place="margin">leb. 13. 17.</note> for elſe it will bee vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them. To others it is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; for by the iuſt praiſe giuen vnto benefactors, others are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to take the greater bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by them, but <hi>cuius perſona con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnitur, eius oratio deſpicitur,</hi> whoſe perſon is contemned, his ſpeech is deſpiſed: there is no ſuch enemie to profit, as preiudicate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; as was ſeene in the countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Chriſt himſelfe, amongſt whom he could doe no great work becauſe of their vnbeliefe. Againe, when others ſee vertue to bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, they are thereby the better ſtirred vp to the ſtudie of the like vertues: ſo that to giue deſerued honour is both iuſt and profitable. Which too much reproueth thoſe that in ſtead of giuing due honour and deſeruing praiſe, loade the beſt deſerued Miniſters with reproach and diſgrace: theſe ſhould know whoſe Meſſengers they wrong &amp; abuſe, euen the meſſengers of the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14574:50"/> Lord of hoſts, who will not ſuffer ſuch wrongs vnreuenged. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (beloued) let vs endeauour on all ſides, in the firſt place to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance Gods honour; and ſecondly, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that the teachers ſtriuing to ſoundneſſe and ſincereneſſe in their doctrines; and they, together with the people, to perſeuerance &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie in faith, and in manners, both ſeeking the praiſe and honour of God, neither may be depriued of ſuch honor &amp; praiſe, as God vſeth to giue vnto his Saints &amp; ſeruants.</p>
            <p>Now the God of all glory and honour, and the giuer of all grace to them that doe him honour, make vs all walke by one rule, &amp; to ſeeke that honour that commeth of God, and not of men. To this God onely wiſe, the Trinity in vnity, be giuen and aſcribed in the Congregations, all praiſe, and honour, and glory, &amp; Maieſty, and might, by vs and all, both now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Soli deo gloria.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
